Guide to the Javier Pérez de Cuéllar Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Javier Pérez de Cuéllar papers
1980-1992
MS 1768
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
17
The papers consist of photocopies of United Nations documents used in the writing of Javier Pérez de Cuéllar's memoirs, Pilgrimage for Peace: A Secretary-General's Memoir. His biography recounts his two terms as United Nations Secretary-General, focusing on those issues and countries with which he had the largest personal involvement.
Pérez de Cuéllar, Javier, 1920-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Javier Javier Pérez de Cuéllar, 2000.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Javier Pérez de Cuéllar was born on January 19, 1920 in Peru. Upon completion of his law studies in 1944, he entered the Peruvian career diplomatic service, serving on the delegation to the Preparatory Commission of the United Nations and in a variety of capacities in the foreign ministry in Lima. He also served as ambassador to Switzerland in 1962 and to the Soviet Union in 1968. In 1970 he became the Permanent Representative of Peru in the United Nations and served twice as President of the Security Council. In 1975 he became the Special Representative for Cyprus. He was recalled by his government in 1977 to serve as ambassador to Venezuela and in 1979 assumed the post of Under-Secretary-General for Special Political Affairs at the United Nations. He was elected Secretary-General of the United Nations in 1982, serving two terms until 1992. Javier Pérez de Cuéllar is the author of Pilgrimage for Peace: A Secretary-General's Memoir.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of photocopies of United Nations documents used in the writing of Javier Pérez de Cuéllar's memoirs, Pilgrimage for Peace: A Secretary-General's Memoir. His biography recounts his two terms as United Nations Secretary-General, focusing on those issues and countries with which he had the largest personal involvement.
Falkland Islands War, 1982; Statesmen -- Peru; Africa -- Politics and government -- 1960-; Cambodia -- Politics and government -- 1979-; Central America -- Politics and government -- 1979-; Latin America -- Politics and government -- 20th Century; Middle East -- Politics and government -- 1979-; Yugoslavia -- Politics and government -- 1980-1992; Pérez de Cuéllar, Javier, 1920-; United Nations; United Nations. Secretary-General
- Inventory, 1980-1992
  Scope and Contents
  The Javier Pérez de Cuéllar Papers consist of photocopies of United Nations documents used in the writing of Pilgrimage for Peace. The photocopies include reports of the General Assembly and the Security Council, briefing notes, summaries of meetings with officials of numerous countries, and related items. The listing parallels the arrangement of the chapters in the book, beginning with Part Two, "The Middle East and Beyond" through Part V, "Restoring Peace on Two Continents." Miscellaneous files are included at the end of the collection.
  - Part Two: The Middle East and Beyond
    - "Battle for Lebanon" [chapter three]
      - Lebanon, 1982-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 7)
      - Lebanon/UNIFIL [United Nations Interim Force in Lebanon], 1982 (Box 1, Folder 8 - 9)
      - Middle East/UNIFIL troop contributor meeting, 1982-1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Middle East/Lebanon, 1986-1991 (Box 2, Folder 11 - 13)
    - "Working for a Middle East Peace Settlement" [chapter four]
      - Middle East/UNIFIL, 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Middle East/Syria, 1982-1988 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Middle East/Israel, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 16 - 17)
      - Middle East International Conference, 1984-1991 (Box 2, Folder 18 - 24)
    - "The Decisive Issue: The Palestinians" [chapter five]
      - Occupied territories, 1982-1989 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Occupied territories [not used], 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - TWA hijacking, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - United Nations Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees in the Near East (UNRWA), 1982-1985 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - United Nations Department of Public Information (UNDOF), 1987 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Palestine [miscellaneous papers], 1984-1986, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - Middle East [documents and text], 1988-1990 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - Middle East [miscellaneous papers], 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - Middle East [notes for the file], 1982-1989 (Box 3, Folder 33 - 34)
      - Peace process, 1982-1991 (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - Middle East trip, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 36 - 38)
      - Middle East/Jordan, 1982-1990 (Box 4, Folder 39)
      - Egypt, 1983-1989 (Box 4, Folder 40)
      - Middle East, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 41)
      - Middle East attack on Iraqi nuclear installation, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 42)
      - Middle East/general, 1982-1991 (Box 4, Folder 43 - 48)
      - Missing documents/questions [re publication], 1982-1991 (Box 4, Folder 49)
      - PLO mission to New York, 1982-1989 (Box 5, Folder 50 - 51)
      - Middle East PLO, 1989, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 52 - 53)
      - Special Advisor on Economic Development in Occupied Palestinian Territories (Francis Blanchard), 1988-1991 (Box 5, Folder 54)
      - International Conference on the Question of Palestine, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 55)
      - Palestine, 1983-1984 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - "Hostages!" [chapter six]
      - Hostages, 1985-1991 (Box 5, Folder 57)
      - Collett, Alec, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 58)
      - Higgins, William, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - "An Unending War" [chapter seven]
      - Iran/Iraq, 1980-1993 (Box 5, Folder 60 - 65)
      - Iran/Iraq, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 66 - 73)
      - Iran/Iraq, 1988-1989 (Box 7, Folder 74 - 82)
      - Iran/Iraq, 1989-1993 (Box 8, Folder 83 - 86)
      - Iran/Iraq US role, 1982, 1987-1988 (Box 8, Folder 87)
    - "Afghanistan: A Victory Betrayed" [chapter eight]
      - Afghanistan [documents], 1982-1991 (Box 8, Folder 88)
      - Afghanistan [miscellaneous papers], 1988 (Box 8, Folder 89)
      - Afghanistan and Middle East War, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 90)
      - Afghanistan, 1980-1984 (Box 8, Folder 91 - 93)
      - Afghanistan, 1984-1988 (Box 9, Folder 94 - 101)
      - Afghanistan, 1988-1991 (Box 10, Folder 102 - 110)
      - Afghanistan, 1988-1991 (Box 11, Folder 111 - 115)
    - "Cyprus: Labyrinth with No Exit" [chapter nine]
      - Cyprus, 1982-1984 (Box 11, Folder 116 - 118)
      - Cyprus, 1984-1992 (Box 12, Folder 119 - 126)
      - Conversation with Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher about Cyprus, undated (Box 13, Folder 127)
    - "War in the Gulf" [chapter ten]
      - Kuwait/Iraq pre-war, 1990-1991 (Box 13, Folder 128 - 131)
      - Kuwait, 1988-1991 (Box 13, Folder 132 - 133)
      - Kuwait/Iraq war period, 1990-1991 (Box 13, Folder 134)
      - Kuwait/Iraq resolutions, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 135)
      - Kuwait/Iraq post war, 1990-1992 (Box 14, Folder 136 - 140)
  - Part three: Africa: A Continent of Triumph and Travail
    - "Namibia: Independence at Last" [chapter eleven]
      - Commissions for Namibia, 1982-1987 (Box 14, Folder 141)
      - United Nations Transition Assistance Group (UNTAG)
        - Namibia, 1983, 1988-1990 (Box 14, Folder 142 - 143)
        - Press releases, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 144)
        - Press releases, 1989-1990 (Box 15, Folder 145 - 146)
        - Administration, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 147)
        - Force commander, 1988-1990 (Box 15, Folder 148)
      - Namibia Bi-lateral Tripartite agreements, 1988-1990 (Box 15, Folder 149)
      - Namibia/Mozambique, 1995 (Box 15, Folder 150)
      - Namibia/United States, 1983-1989 (Box 15, Folder 151)
      - Namibia/various countries, 1982-1990 (Box 15, Folder 152)
      - Council for Namibia, 1986-1990 (Box 15, Folder 153)
      - Namibia, 1981-1982 (Box 15, Folder 154 - 156)
      - Namibia, 1982-1984, 1989 (Box 16, Folder 157 - 164)
      - Namibia Western Contact/Five Contact Group, 1982-1983 (Box 16, Folder 165)
      - Council for Namibia, 1982-1986 (Box 16, Folder 166 - 167)
      - Namibia, South Africa, Angola, trips to [Aug 22-28], 1983 (Box 17, Folder 168)
      - Conference on Namibia, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 169)
      - Namibia, 1983-1985 (Box 17, Folder 170 - 176)
      - Namibia, 1985-1988 (Box 18, Folder 177 - 186)
      - Council for Namibia/Sterling Committee, 1986-1987 (Box 18, Folder 187)
      - Namibia, 1983, 1987-1990 (Box 19, Folder 188 - 195)
      - Negotiations with Namibia/Angola, 1988 (Box 19, Folder 196)
      - Namibia, 1989-1990 (Box 20, Folder 197 - 208)
      - Namibia elections, 1989 (Box 20, Folder 209)
      - Namibia, 1989-1991 (Box 21, Folder 210 - 218)
      - Namibia [reports of secretary-general], 1979-1989 (Box 21, Folder 219 - 220)
      - Namibia [report of secretary-general], 1990 (Box 21, Folder 221)
      - SWAPO, 1987-1990 (Box 22, Folder 222)
      - Namibia [secretary-general messages, statements, and days of solidarity], 1982-1984 (Box 22, Folder 223)
    - "Angola and Mozambique: Countries in Crisis" [chapter twelve]
      - Military options in Western Sahara, 1987 (Box 22, Folder 224)
      - Mozambique, 1982-1991 (Box 22, Folder 225 - 226)
      - Nigeria, 1982-1991 (Box 22, Folder 227)
      - Algeria, 1982-1991 (Box 22, Folder 228)
      - Algeria, trip to, 1989 (Box 22, Folder 229)
      - Africa, trip to, 1985 (Box 22, Folder 230)
      - Miscellaneous, 1988 (Box 22, Folder 231)
      - Mozambique, 1982-1983 (Box 22, Folder 232)
      - Africa/Mozambique, trip to [Feb 3-5], 1983 (Box 22, Folder 233)
      - Trips, general, 1986-1990 (Box 22, Folder 234)
      - Peace keeping in Mozambique, 1995 (Box 22, Folder 235)
      - Botswana, trip to [Feb 6-7], 1983 (Box 22, Folder 236)
      - Angola, 1991 (Box 22, Folder 237)
      - Miscellaneous, 1987 (Box 22, Folder 238)
      - United Nations Angola Verification Mission (UNAVEM), 1988-1989 (Box 22, Folder 239)
      - Verification of troop withdrawals, 1988, 1990 (Box 22, Folder 240)
      - Angola/internal UN role, 1990-1991 (Box 23, Folder 241)
      - South African mission to protect UNITA, 1987 (Box 23, Folder 242)
      - Special coordination for emergency relief operations in Angola, 1987-1991 (Box 23, Folder 243)
      - United Republic of Tanzania, 1982-1987 (Box 23, Folder 244)
      - Botswana, 1982-1989 (Box 23, Folder 245)
      - UNAVEM, 1981-1991 (Box 23, Folder 246 - 247)
      - Annex B, 1991 (Box 23, Folder 248)
      - Annex C, 1991 (Box 23, Folder 249)
      - Press conference transcript [secretary-general], 1983 (Box 23, Folder 250)
      - Trip record, 1982-1990 (Box 23, Folder 251)
      - Mozambique, 1982, 1990 (Box 23, Folder 252)
      - Zambia, 1982-1991 (Box 23, Folder 253 - 254)
      - Zimbabwe, 1987-1991 (Box 23, Folder 255)
      - Prisoners/South Africa, 1982, 1984, 1988 (Box 23, Folder 256)
      - South Africa, 1982-1991 (Box 23, Folder 257 - 260)
    - "The Western Sahara" [chapter thirteen]
      - Western Sahara, 1981-1989 (Box 24, Folder 261 - 283)
      - Western Sahara, 1990-1991 (Box 25, Folder 284 - 293)
      - Western Sahara/Morocco, 1982-1990 (Box 25, Folder 294 - 300)
      - Western Sahara/Morocco, 1991 (Box 26, Folder 301 - 302)
      - Western Sahara/Polisario Front, 1983-1991 (Box 26, Folder 303 - 308)
      - Consultative Committee at Nairobi [Feb 6-9], 1982 (Box 26, Folder 309)
      - Casablanca, trip to [Jan 5], 1984 (Box 26, Folder 310)
      - Morocco, trip to [May 1-5], 1988 (Box 26, Folder 311)
      - Morocco, trip to [Jun 18-20], 1989 (Box 26, Folder 312)
      - Technical Survey Mission [Nov 21-Dec 9], 1987 (Box 26, Folder 313)
      - Mission to Sahara [May 1-7], 1988 (Box 26, Folder 314)
      - Special representatives of the secretary-general, 1988-1991 (Box 26, Folder 315)
      - Secretary-general's statement to OAU, 1989 (Box 26, Folder 316)
      - United Nations Mission for the Referendum in Western Sahara (MINURSO)], 1991 (Box 26, Folder 317 - 318)
      - Task Force on Western Sahara, 1991 (Box 26, Folder 319)
      - Zimbabwe, 1983-1986 (Box 27, Folder 320)
      - Trips
        - Angola, 1982-1983 (Box 27, Folder 321)
        - Sudan, 1989 (Box 27, Folder 322)
        - Tanzania, 1983 (Box 27, Folder 323)
        - Zambia, 1983 (Box 27, Folder 324)
        - Zimbabwe, 1983 (Box 27, Folder 325)
  - Part four: War and Peace in Latin America
    - "The Falklands/Malvinas: A Nineteenth-Century War in the Twentieth Century" [chapter fourteen]
      - Falklands, 1982 April-June (Box 27, Folder 326 - 329)
      - Post war, 1982, 1986-1988 (Box 27, Folder 330)
      - Statements of United Kingdom and Argentine positions, 1982 (Box 27, Folder 331)
      - OAS and non aligned, 1982 (Box 27, Folder 332)
    - "The Path to Peace in Central America" [chapter fifteen]
      - Efforts towards peace resolutions, 1991 (Box 27, Folder 333)
      - Letters, 1991 (Box 27, Folder 334)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 27, Folder 335)
      - Central America
        - 1982 (Box 27, Folder 336 - 338)
        - 1983 (Box 28, Folder 339 - 342)
        - 1984 Jan-Jun (Box 28, Folder 343 - 344)
        - 1984-1985 (Box 29, Folder 345 - 352)
        - 1985-1987 (Box 30, Folder 353 - 359)
        - 1987-1988 (Box 31, Folder 360 - 366)
        - 1988 (Box 32, Folder 367 - 368)
        - 1989 (Box 32, Folder 369 - 373)
        - 1989-1991 (Box 33, Folder 374 - 381)
      - El Salvador
        - 1989-1990 (Box 33, Folder 382 - 383)
        - 1990 (Box 34, Folder 384 - 388)
        - 1991 Jan-Dec (Box 34, Folder 389 - 393)
        - 1991 Jul-Dec (Box 35, Folder 394 - 395)
      - Guatemala, 1989-1991 (Box 35, Folder 396)
      - Guatemala/Cuba, 1989-1991 (Box 35, Folder 397 - 398)
      - Cuba, trip to [May 28-31], 1985 (Box 35, Folder 399)
      - Honduras, 1990 (Box 35, Folder 400)
      - Nicaragua, 1989-1990 (Box 35, Folder 401 - 405)
      - Conversation with James Baker on Nicaragua [Feb 2], 1990 (Box 36, Folder 406)
      - Meeting with Violeta Chamorro [Sep 27], 1990 (Box 36, Folder 407)
      - Nicaragua, 1991 (Box 36, Folder 408)
      - United Nations Observer Group in Central America (ONUCA), 1988-1991 (Box 36, Folder 409 - 410)
      - Haiti, 1985-1991 (Box 36, Folder 411 - 419)
  - Part five: Restoring Peace on Two Continents
    - "Cambodia: Rebirth of a Nation" [chapter sixteen]
      - Cambodia, 1982-1990 (Box 37, Folder 420 - 430)
      - Cambodia, 1991 (Box 38, Folder 431 - 432)
      - Cambodian refugees, 1982-1983, 1990-1991 (Box 38, Folder 433)
      - Kampuchea, 1982-1989 (Box 38, Folder 434 - 442)
      - Internal conditions, 1990-1991 (Box 38, Folder 443)
      - Romanian aspect, 1987 (Box 38, Folder 444)
      - Financial considerations and Japan, 1990 (Box 38, Folder 445)
      - Notes of the secretary-general's meeting with the special representative for humanitarian affairs in the Southeast, 1991 (Box 38, Folder 446)
      - Notes of the secretary-general's meeting with the minister of foreign affairs to Indonesia, 1991 (Box 38, Folder 447)
      - Paris meeting with Supreme National Council [Jan 8], 1991 (Box 38, Folder 448)
      - Notes for the secretary-general, 1991 (Box 38, Folder 449)
      - Paris Peace Conference papers, 1989 (Box 38, Folder 450)
      - Final statement of United Nations Transitional Authority in Cambodia (UNTAC), 1990 (Box 38, Folder 451)
    - "Yugoslavia: A European Tragedy" [chapter seventeen]
      - Yugoslavia, 1982-1990 (Box 38, Folder 452 - 460)
        - 1991 (Box 39, Folder 461 - 466)
  - Miscellaneous files
    - United Kingdom, 1982-1991 (Box 39, Folder 467 - 475)
    - Germany, 1982-1991 (Box 40, Folder 476 - 477)
    - China, 1987 (Box 40, Folder 478)
    - UN contacts with the Soviet Union, 1984 (Box 40, Folder 479)
    - USSR, 1982-1991 (Box 40, Folder 480 - 489)
    - Secretary-general's schedules/speeches, 1982-1991 (Box 40, Folder 490)
    - Secretary-general's meeting with Vice President Quayle [Dec 11], 1989 (Box 40, Folder 491)
    - United States, 1982-1988 (Box 40, Folder 492 - 498)
      - Miscellaneous contacts, 1982-1988 (Box 40, Folder 499 - 505)
        - 1987-1991 (Box 41, Folder 506 - 510)